<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Program-specific issues">
  <p>
    If you have trouble with the following programs....
  </p>
  <toc/>

  <!-- *************************************************** -->

  <stockmsg id="nosiopatch">
    <p>
      Unmodified versions of this game contain a RTCLOK check during the disk load and must be
      booted with the SIO patch disabled.
    </p>
  </stockmsg>

  <stockmsg id="diskrw">
    <p>
      This program writes to the disk during normal operation and requires read/write or virtual
      read/write mode to be selected.
    </p>
  </stockmsg>
  
  <!-- *************************************************** -->

  <h2>Demos</h2>
  <h3>1st Top Demo 1989</h3>
  <p>
    Contains a direct jump into the XL/XE OS at $C0E2 and may fail with other OSes.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Cup of Tea</h3>
  <p>
    There is a bug in the IRQ handling that causes it to occasionally crash after playing
    the sample: it assumes that an IRQ cannot happen after it is shut off in IRQEN, but there is
    a one-cycle window where this can still occur.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Total Daze</h3>
  <p>
    Due to a bug in the detection routine, this demo occasionally misdetects a single POKEY as
    dual POKEYs, resulting in garbled audio during the loading screen.
  </p>

  <!-- *************************************************** -->

  <h2>Games</h2>

  <h3>Alien Garden</h3>
  <p>
    Erroneously trips GTIA video modes, resulting in colored garbage on screen during transitions.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Assault Force 3D</h3>
  <p>
    This game requires the SuperCharger 3D cartridge, which is used for hardware multiply/divide.
  </p>

  <h3>Berzerk</h3>
  <p>
    Some versions do not initialize SKCTL properly and therefore fail to play shot sounds.
  </p>

  <h3>Bounty Bob Strikes Back!</h3>
  <p>
    Some versions require <b>exactly</b> 64K of RAM to work.
  </p>

  <h3>Bubble Bobble (demo)</h3>
  <p>
    Some versions of this homebrew game copy the kernel into RAM, write over part of the SIO
    routine, and then invoke the corrupted SIO routine. This will only work in some emulators
    when SIO patch is enabled, bypassing the broken code; it does not work in Altirra because
    SIO hooks are not allowed to activate from code in RAM.
  </p>

  <h3>Castle Wolfenstein</h3>
  <stockref id="diskrw"/>

  <h3>Choplifter (cartridge)</h3>
  <p>
    Copies out OS ROM at addresses $E500-FEFF and $C500-CBFF, and so can fail with OSes other
    than the stock XL/XE OS.
  </p>

  <h3>DARG</h3>
  <p>
    The clock runs too quickly if accelerated floating-point is enabled.
  </p>

  <h3>E.T. Phone Home!</h3>
  <p>
    This cartridge has a protection check which requires the OS to boot within a certain
    amount of time. The XL/XE OS takes more time to initialize and can cause this check to
    fail on NTSC systems.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Gruds in Space</h3>
  <stockref id="nosiopatch"/>
  
  <h3>His Dark Majesty</h3>
  <p>
    Version 1.0 has a bug that can cause it to crash if the opening animation is interrupted due
    to infinite DLI interrupts. The workaround is to hit a key during the title screen instead.
    This bug is fixed in version 1.01.
  </p>
  <p>
    This game will not work with some custom OSes due to copying out parts of the OS ROM for
    private use (the SIO routines, to be specific).
  </p>

  <h3>Mr. DO!</h3>
  <p>
    Unmodified versions should be run with the SIO patch disabled. The game may appear to load
    correctly, but will malfunction in certain game elements due to the silently failed timing
    check.
  </p>
  
  <h3>M.U.L.E.</h3>
  <p>
    The tiny sound glitches that occur when notes are played happen on a real Atari, too.
  </p>

  <h3>Parsec XL</h3>
  <p>
    Directly jumps into XL/XE OS at $C28A and may fail with other OSes.
  </p>

  <h3>Preppie II</h3>
  <p>
    Has hidden a function in the game that skips levels if the button on paddle 4 or 5 is pressed.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Transylvania</h3>
  <stockref id="nosiopatch"/>

  <h3>Twerps</h3>
  <stockref id="nosiopatch"/>

  <h3>Ultima I</h3>
  <p>
    This game requires the OS-B kernel ROM to run. It fails on HLE or XL kernels because it has
    hardcoded references to keyboard translation tables in the OS-B ROM.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Zebuland</h3>
  <stockref id="diskrw"/>

  <!-- *************************************************** -->

  <h2>Applications</h2>
  <h3>FoReM XL/XE/XE Pro</h3>
  <p>
    FoReM relies on particular short response values for CONNECT messages from the modem.
    These were not standardized for higher baud rates. Altirra's emulated modem returns the Conexant
    code for 9600 baud (12), while FoReM by default expects the value returned by U.S. Robotics
    modems (13). Either lower the connection speed limit to 2400 baud or follow the directions in the FXL/FXE
    documentation to change the expected code.
  </p>
  <p>
    The clock in FoReM XL/XE also tends to lose a couple of seconds per day because it is
    written to expect exactly 60 or 50 frames per second, whereas the actual Atari runs slightly
    slower than that (59.92 fps / 49.87 fps). A workaround is to adjust the emulator speed to
    50/60Hz in Speed Options.
  </p>
  <h3>Ice-T XE 2.72</h3>
  <p>
    The keyboard click feature of this program has a bug: it calls directly into the OS K:
    handler's GET BYTE routine without going through CIO and without setting ICAX1Z. This
    causes the program to sometimes jam up endlessly transmitting the "j" character. Disabling
    the keyboard click and then waiting for the output buffer to drain fixes the problem.
  </p>
  <p>
    This bug is fixed in Ice-T XE 2.73.
  </p>
  
  <!-- *************************************************** -->
  
  <h2>Disk Operating Systems</h2>
  <h3>MyDOS</h3>
  <p>
    The Load Binary command in the MyDOS menu uses a MyDOS-specific XIO call to load the binary
    instead of regular CIO read calls. This prevents Load Binary from working with the H: handler
    as the handler does not know how to handle MyDOS XIO calls.
  </p>
  <p>
    There is also a bug in MyDOS that prevents wildcarded copies from working when using H: as
    the source: MyDOS passes the wrong flags when enumerating files from non-disk devices, causing
    the copy to fail. Specifically, it attempts to read a directory listing using an <tt>AUX1</tt> mode
    of <tt>$04</tt> (open file) instead of <tt>$06</tt> (open directory).
  </p>
  <h3>SpartaDOS 3.2</h3>
  <p>
    While the emulator's H: device can be accessed by SpartaDOS 3, there is a bug in its COPY
    command that causes it to malfunction when copying from H: to a destination path:
  </p>
  <blockquote>
    <tt>D1:>COPY H:FILE.BIN D2:</tt>
  </blockquote>
  <p>
    This fails with <tt>163 Illegal wildcard in name</tt> because COPY attempts to create a file
    called <tt>*.*</tt> on the destination drive. It works for copies from the regular <tt>D:</tt>
    device because there it issues a directory search to get the source name. The workaround is
    to specify a full destination filename:
  </p>
  <blockquote>
    <tt>D1:>COPY H:FILE.BIN D2:FILE.BIN</tt>
  </blockquote>
  <h3>SpartaDOS X</h3>  
  <p>
    SpartaDOS X uses a polling loop for SIO transfers, so regular burst I/O mode does not work
    with it. Use the burst (polled) mode instead.
  </p>
  <p>
    The H: device is not supported at all by the SDX kernel, so specific drivers or tools must
    be used to copy to and from the emulator devices. <a href="pclink.html">PCLink</a> is the
    recommended alternative for SDX 4.44 and above.
  </p>
</topic>