<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Symbol options">
  <h2>Default bank handling</h2>
  <p>
    By default, the debugger treats any address in an extended bank as separate from the main bank. This includes addresses
    above bank 0 in 65C816 mode, as well as PORTB and cartridge bank global addresses. This prevents bogus mapping of main
    bank symbols to extended banks.
  </p>
  <p>
    When using listings from the <tt>MADS</tt> assembler, symbols in extended banks are interpreted as being in 65C816
    linear memory. This can be changed by using <i>symbol options</i> to change the interpretation of banks.
  </p>
  <h2>Supported symbol options</h2>
  <p>
    Symbols can be defined with special names to influence how the debugger interprets labels emitted by the assembler/linker.
    Only the name of the symbol is used; the value may be any address, to allow them to be placed out of the way for programs
    that might interpret them as regular symbols. The address <tt>$FFFF</tt> is recommended for this purpose. The debugger
    will remove any symbol that it recognizes as an option.
  </p>
  <p>
    Symbol options only apply to the file they are declared in. The order of the symbol options and the symbols they affect
    does not matter.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>Note</b>: The names of all symbol options begin with <i>two</i> underscores.
  </p>
  <dl>
    <dt><tt>__ATBANK_</tt>xx<tt>_RAM</tt></dt>
    <dd>
      Interpret symbols in bank <tt>$xx</tt> as being in RAM. This is used for cartridges
      that can be disabled, exposing the main RAM underneath.
    </dd>
    
    <dt><tt>__ATBANK_</tt>xx<tt>_CART</tt></dt>
    <dd>
      Interpret symbols in bank <tt>$xx</tt> within <tt>$A000-BFFF</tt> as being in cartridge space, instead of PORTB space.
    </dd>
    
    <dt><tt>__ATBANK_00_GLOBAL</tt></dt>
    <dd>
      Interpret all symbols in bank 0 as global symbols, mapping to that address in any bank.
    </dd>
  </dl>
</topic>
