<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Indus GT">
	<p>
		The Indus GT disk drive supports single-density (90K), enhanced density (130K), and
		double density (180K) disks. It does not support double-sided disks, however.
	</p>
	<h2>Booting Indus CP/M</h2>
	<p>
		Altirra's Indus GT emulation includes the RAMCharger, which means that it can run
		Indus CP/M. The trickiest part of booting Indus CP/M is obtaining a working image
		of it. The disk is a double-density disk with 256 byte boot sectors, which is unusual.
		Some images of this disk encoded in the .ATR file format are corrupted because they
		only hold the first 128 bytes of the the first three sectors. To boot properly,
		the full 256 byte contents of these sectors are required, which cannot be encoded
		safely in .ATR. A working image of the Indus CP/M disk must be encoded in .XFD for
		the emulator to use it.
	</p>
	<p>
		A good image of Indus CP/M disk must be paired with an accompanying boot disk for
		the computer, which acts as the terminal. The procedure for booting CP/M is as follows:
	</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Boot the terminal disk on the computer.</li>
		<li>Start the terminal program (typically E.COM or F.COM, for 40 and 80 column operation).</li>
		<li>Remove the terminal disk and insert the CP/M disk. This must be done without rebooting
			the computer, so the Open Image, Disk Drive dialog, or Attach disk commands should be
			used instead. Alternately, mounting both disks on D1: and D2: and using the rotate disk
			commands can be convenient.
		</li>
		<li>
			Instruct the Indus drive to boot CP/M by holding Drive Type and pressing Error. This
			is not possible in the emulator, so a special command has been added to do it:
			System, Console Switches, Indus GT: Boot CP/M.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
		If everything has been done correctly, CP/M will boot and be displayed in the terminal:
	</p>
	<img src="pics/indus-cpm.png" />
	<h2>Interleaving performance issue</h2>
	<p>
		When using Indus CP/M, it's best to leave the Accurate Disk Timing option disabled. The
		reason is that the emulator is unable to determine that the CP/M disk image should have
		a different sector interleave than a normal double-density disk, and so it will apply
		a 15:1 interleave to the disk. This will make CP/M load extremely slowly since it,
		operating directly on the disk drive, expects a 1:1 interleave instead.
	</p>
</topic>