<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Introduction: cassette tape devices">
  <p>
    Cassette tape was used as a low-cost storage option prior to widespread availability of
    faster and more reliable disk drives. First-party cassette tape devices included the Atari
    410, 1010, and XC12 Program Recorders.
  </p>
  <h2>Supported image formats</h2>
  <p>
    Tape images can be stored in one of two formats, pre-decoded (CAS) and raw audio.
  </p>
  <h3>CAS format</h3>
  <p>
    CAS files are the most common format for tape image storage and contain the data
    track pre-decoded to binary data. These are generally small, compact files as they are not
    much bigger than the stored program. CAS files cannot contain an audio track.
  </p>
  <p>
    The original CAS format can only contain data using serial byte framing and can't
    store non-byte data, such as audio synchronization timing marks used by some learning
    software. Extensions to the CAS format do allow for storing raw FSK data or turbo (PWM)
    data, and these extensions are supported by Altirra.
  </p>
  <h3>Raw audio format</h3>
  <p>
    Altirra also supports reading and decoding raw audio files. This is the most flexible
    option as it gives the emulator full control over tape decoding without needing the
    tape to be pre-converted, especially with tricky scenarios like mixed FSK and turbo
    encoded data. It also supports full emulation of tapes that have an audio track. Raw
    audio files are very large and unwieldy, however.
  </p>
  <h3>Hybrid format</h3>
  <p>
    As of 4.30+, Altirra also supports loading from a hybrid pair of a pre-decoded CAS image for the
    data track and a mono Ogg Vorbis compressed audio track. This reduces the storage
    requirements while still providing audio support.
  </p>
  <h2>Booting a tape</h2>
  <p>
    You can boot a program from a tape image using the Boot Image command and selecting the CAS or audio file.
    Altirra will automatically load the tape image, unload other conflicting images according to boot
    settings, and auto-start the tape load if tape auto boot is enabled.
  </p>
  <h3>Machine-language programs</h3>
  <p>
    The Atari OS has provisions for booting machine language programs from cassette tape. This
    is done by holding down the Start button while booting the computer. The computer emits one
    buzz to prompt the user to press Play on the cassette tape player and then hit a key,
    after which the computer begins loading from tape.
  </p>
  <p>
    The emulator can automate this if the <i>System / Cassette / Auto-Boot on Startup</i> option
    is enabled; this causes the emulator to both hold down Start and then press the Space Bar.
  </p>
  <h3>BASIC programs</h3>
  <p>
    If the cassette tape has a BASIC program, it cannot be booted via the above procedure. Instead,
    the BASIC interpreter must be started first and then the <tt>CLOAD</tt> command issued. As
    with the ML boot, the computer will buzz once when ready and a key should be pressed after
    the tape player is ready in Play mode.
  </p>
  <h3>Automatic ML/BASIC switching</h3>
  <p>
    If the <i>Auto-boot BASIC on startup</i> option is enabled, the emulator will attempt to detect
    whether the program starts with a machine-language or BASIC program and configure the boot
    process accordingly, including enabling or disabling BASIC and issuing commands to start
    the BASIC load process. In some rare cases this detection may fail, in which case a manual
    <tt>CLOAD</tt> or <tt>RUN "C"</tt> may be needed.
  </p>
  <h2>Tapes with audio tracks</h2>
  <p>
    Atari tapes are recorded in stereo and have an audio track that is piped through the
    computer to the TV set. This means that music and speech can be played while a program
    is loading. Altirra emulates this if you load a suitable tape recording in raw audio
    format as a cassette tape.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>NOTE</b>&#xA0; The <tt>.cas</tt> format has no provision for an audio track. Tapes
    loaded in CAS will never have an audio track and resaving a <tt>.wav</tt> tape as CAS
    will drop the audio.
  </p>
  <h2>Accelerating tape I/O</h2>
  <p>
    Loading from tape is extremely slow by modern standards. The standard tape routines in the OS
    use a baud rate of 600 baud with a quarter-second gap between 128 byte records, so the average
    throughput is about 50 bytes per second. This means that longer programs can take as long as
    10 minutes to load at authentic speeds. The emulator displays the current tape position as
    both a time code and percentage to indicate load progress, but it still takes a long time.
  </p>
  <p>
    The emulator's warp speed can be used to speed this up somewhat without affecting accuracy, but
    Altirra has an even faster path for loading from tape. Enabling the C: SIO patch will cause
    the emulator to intercept tape load requests to the OS and handle them directly. This loads programs
    in seconds instead of minutes. However, it can't be used with non-standard formats or loaders
    that directly access the serial port hardware.
  </p>
  <h2>Tape control</h2>
  <p>
    By default, the emulator rewinds the tape to the beginning and puts the cassette tape
    deck in Play mode on power-up. This is fine for most simple uses, but for more complex
    scenarios, the <i>Tape Control</i> dialog can be used to control the emulated tape recorder.
  </p>
  <div style="text-align: center">
    <img src="pics/tapecontrol.png" />
  </div>
  <p>
    The tape control dialog contains the normal controls of a tape recorder, including
    Stop, Pause, Play, and Record. Seeking controls are slightly different: instead of
    having Rewind and Fast Forward, two buttons allow for seeking to the beginning or
    the end, and intermediate seeking is done either by dragging the position slider or
    clicking on the waveform graph.
  </p>
  <p>
    The waveform graph shows the two channels of the tape. Atari 8-bit tapes are
    stereo and contain an audio track (left channel, red) and data track (right channel, blue).
    The waveform shown for these two tracks makes it easier to find the records on the
    tape.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>WARNING</b>&#xA0; While the computer can stop or start the cassette tape motor,
    it cannot detect whether the tape drive is moving or whether it is in Play or Record
    mode. Like on a real 410/1010, if you try to load a program with the tape drive in
    Record mode instead of Play mode, the emulator will happily record blank tape over
    the program you are trying to load. Similarly, trying to save a program while the
    tape drive is Stopped or Paused will produce the right sounds but nothing on the tape.
  </p>
  <h2>Other considerations</h2>
  <h3>Minimal leader</h3>
  <p>
    When loading a <tt>.cas</tt> file, Altirra checks if the leader at the beginning of
    the tape is at least 10 seconds and extends it to that amount if needed. The reason
    for this is that the Operating System waits nine seconds after starting the motor
    before trying to read from the cassette tape in order to skip past leader noise.
    Normally this isn't a problem because the OS writes an 18 second leader when it
    records to tape, but it can be an issue if part of the leader was dropped when the
    tape was digitized to an image file.
  </p>
</topic>