<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="On-screen indicators">
  <p>
    A series of on-screen indicators can appear at the bottom of the display window to indicate I/O activity.
  </p>
  <img src="pics/indicators.png" width="672" height="38" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"/>
  <p>
    The indicators are as follows:
  </p>
  <blockquote>
    <dl>
      <dt>Modem status (Connected to 192.168.0.1:8000)</dt>
      <dd>
        Displays outgoing addresses and state when dialing out and incoming addresses and state when receiving connections.
        Addresses are displayed in raw IPv4 or IPv6 format.
      </dd>

      <dt>Cassette tape position (00:00:00)</dt>
      <dd>
        Appears when a cassette tape image is mounted and the cassette tape is moving. A "C" is also displayed before
        the timestamp when cassette SIO acceleration is occurring.
      </dd>

      <dt>PCLink activity (PCL:R/W)</dt>
      <dd>
        Displayed when the <a href="pclink.html">PCLink device</a> is activated.
      </dd>

      <dt>Recording length (R02:00:00)</dt>
      <dd>
        Shows how long a video or audio recording session has run.
      </dd>

      <dt>IDE read/write indicator (W1000000)</dt>
      <dd>
        Indicates "R" for read or "W" for write activity to the IDE hard disk and the logical block address (LBA) of the accessed sector.
      </dd>

      <dt>Flash write indicator (F)</dt>
      <dd>
        An "F" is displayed whenever writes occur to cartridge or peripheral flash memory.
      </dd>

      <dt>Floppy drive LEDs (1-15)</dt>
      <dd>
        Appear on a floppy drive access. By default the drive number is displayed; this can be changed to the sector
        number in the menu under <em>System &gt; Disk</em>.
      </dd>
    </dl>
  </blockquote>
  <h2><a name="audiomonitor">Audio Monitor</a></h2>
  <p>
    When the Audio Monitor is enabled, the state of POKEY's four channels is displayed in the lower-left corner:
  </p>
    
  <img src="pics/indicators-audiomonitor.png" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" />
  
  <p>
    Channels 1-4 are shown in order from top to bottom. If stereo POKEY mode is enabled, then a second audio monitor
    is shown at the lower-right corner with channels 1-4 on the second (right) POKEY.
  </p>
  <p>
    For each channel, the following are shown:
  </p>
  <blockquote>
    <dl>
      <dt>Estimated frequency (large number)</dt>
      <dd>
        Half the rate at which the timer is counting. For the square wave (toggle) setting, this is
        the fundamental frequency of the output. For distortion modes or when special effects are
        being played, the main frequency may be a harmonic or subdivision of this frequency.
      </dd>

      <dt>Clock rate (15K/64K/1.79/16)</dt>
      <dd>
        Shows the clock being input to the channel's timer. For audio playback, this is typically
        the 64KHz clock, though all channels can be gang-switched to the 15KHz clock instead.
        Channels 1 and 3 can also be individually switched to the 1.79MHz master clock.
      </dd>
      <dd>
        When channels are linked, the clock rate is not shown and '16' is shown instead, to indicate
        that the high channel is being clocked with the output of the lower channel.
      </dd>

      <dt>Audio clock input (L/5)</dt>
      <dd>
        Indicates the clock input to the audio half of the channel. '<tt>L</tt>' indicates that
        the standard timer clock is being used, while '<tt>5</tt>' means that clock pulses are
        being filtered by the 5-bit noise generator.
      </dd>

      <dt>Audio waveform selection (T/4/9/17/V)</dt>
      <dd>
        Shows the type of waveform produced by the clocked portion of the audio circuit: '<tt>T</tt>'
        for toggle (square wave), '<tt>4</tt>' for 4-bit noise, '<tt>9</tt>' for 9-bit noise,
        '<tt>17</tt>' for 17-bit noise, and '<tt>V</tt>' for volume-only output.
      </dd>

      <dt>High-pass filter (H) (channels 1 and 2 only)</dt>
      <dd>
        '<tt>H</tt>' indicates that channel 1 or 2 is being high-pass filtered using the
        timer output of channel 3 or 4.
      </dd>

      <dt>Two-tone mode (2) (channels 1 and 2 only)</dt>
      <dd>
        '<tt>2</tt>' is shown on channel 1 or 2 when two-tone mode is enabled. The frequency
        estimate is also adjusted to take the extra two-cycle delay into account.
      </dd>

      <dt>Asynchronous receive mode (A) (channels 3 and 4 only)</dt>
      <dd>
        '<tt>A</tt>' is shown on channels 3 and 4 when asynchronous mode is enabled, which
        halts timers 3 and 4 except when data is being received over the serial I/O bus.
        This mode is enabled during disk access and typically needs to be shut off before
        playing audio, or else channels 3 and 4 will be silent.
      </dd>

      <dt>Output waveform and level</dt>
      <dd>
        The right portion of the graph shows the output level and waveform for each channel.
        The vertical bar on the left shows the volume level, while the graph shows the
        channel's audio output as the volume-modulated audio waveform.
      </dd>
      <dd>
        From left to right, the output is shown from the beginning to the end of the frame.
        There is often a break in the waveform near the end of the waveform; this corresponds
        to the beginning of vertical blank, where it is common to run music routines and
        update the audio registers.
      </dd>
      <dd>
        The waveform is sampled on each scanline. Dynamic effects from high-speed changes to
        the audio registers are shown, but the displayed waveform may be inaccurate if changes
        are made at faster than scanline granularity.
      </dd>
    </dl>
  </blockquote>
</topic>