<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="index.xsl" ?>
<topic title="Raw tape images">
  <h2>Supported raw image types</h2>
  <p>
    Altirra supports three different formats for raw tape images:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      Microsoft WAV (<tt>*.wav</tt>), in uncompressed 8-bit or 16-bit per channel
      PCM formats.
    </li>
    <li>
      Free Lossless Audio Codec (<tt>*.flac</tt>)
    </li>
    <li>
      Ogg Vorbis (<tt>*.ogg</tt>)
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    Raw audio files used as tape images may either be mono or stereo. Stereo is
    authentic in capturing the separate audio and data tracks, with the left
    track being audio and right track being data. A mono audio file is treated
    either as a tape with no audio or data duplicated on the audio track,
    depending on the <i>Load Data as Audio</i> option.
  </p>
  <p>
    When loading a raw audio file, Altirra decodes the data track (right channel)
    into digital data using both FSK and turbo decoders. This allows turbo
    decoding to work without the emulator having to detect whether regions
    are FSK or turbo encoded.
  </p>
  <h2>Making a good recording</h2>
  <p>
    Not all programs recorded on tape have audio tracks, but those that do need
    to be recorded in <b>stereo</b> since the audio and data are stored in
    the left and right channels. Some programs take advantage of this and
    read data from the data track while audio is playing.
  </p>
  <p>
    Good quality recordings of a tape are best done with the peak volume level
    a little bit below maximum -- enough to be loud enough without clipping.
    Standard FSK encoding is insensitive to volume level and can often decode
    even with clipping or very low volume levels, but it is still better to
    record with a well-tuned volume level. Turbo encodings are more sensitive
    and especially can break with clipping from excessive volume.
  </p>
  <h3>Leader</h3>
  <p>
    Cassette tapes typically start with a short leader strip that connects the magnetic
    tape to the hub. This leader cannot be recorded on. To accommodate this, the
    cassette tape routines in the OS by default record a 20 second leader when
    saving a file. In turn, the first 10 seconds when loading to avoid misinterpreting
    the noise from the leader as the start of a file.
  </p>
  <p>
    The impact of this is that the leader at the start of a tape should not be skipped
    or removed when imaging a tape. This can prevent the tape from working properly
    if the 10 second skip in the loading process also skips part of the first block.
    The noise from the leader can be silenced, however.
  </p>
  <h3>Audio enhancements</h3>
  <p>
    If possible, any audio enhancements such as bass boost or Dolby Noise Reduction
    should be disabled when recording the tape. These apply equalization curves
    intended to improve sound reproduction and are often meant to be matched against
    a similar filter in the encoder. Computer tape drives don't use pre-emphasis or
    bass/treble enhancement and thus apply such decoding enhancements can distort
    the data track waveform.
  </p>
  <p>
    The standard recording format based on frequency shift keying (FSK) is relatively
    insensitive to such distortions and will generally decode fine with a clean tape
    even if playback enhancements are enabled.
    However, toggling off audio enhancement can make the difference for whether a marginal
    tape can be decoded. Turbo encodings are much more sensitive to waveform distortion
    and should always be recorded without enhancement if possible, even for a clean
    tape.
  </p>
  <h3>Lossy audio compression</h3>
  <p>
    Lossless audio formats such as WAV and FLAC are recommended for most successful
    decoding and preservation. A major reason for this is that most popular lossy audio
    compression algorithms like MP3 and Vorbis are designed to take advantage of
    the human audio perception and can introduce artifacts into the data track
    that corrupt recorded computer tape data. Turbo encodings are especially
    susceptible. Raising the encoding bitrate or quality factor reduces but does not eliminate
    the possibility of data corruption.
  </p>
  <p>
    That having been said, a lossily-compressed audio file can still often be
    decoded if the data was recorded with the standard 600 bit/sec FSK encoding. This is more
    likely with adequate bitrate and a high-quality encoder, such as a 128kbps
    MP3 encoded with LAME. Disabling stereo channel coupling (mid/side or intensity stereo)
    also reduces the chances of cross-artifacts between the data and audio tracks.
  </p>
  <h3>Recording TV audio as a tape</h3>
  <p>
    What won't work is connecting the audio output of an actual Atari to a PC and recording the
    Atari's sound output as a tape. While the sound
    sent to the TV sounds similar to the tape recording, it's different than
    the SIO tape output and has
    additional carrier noise and phase errors. Attempting
    to decode such a recording can work but typically just results in a lot of
    bit errors.
  </p>
  <p>
    The above assumes recording through a line-in connection. What <i>really</i> won't
    work is attempting to record the TV speaker output with a microphone. This generally produces
    a completely undecodable tape due to distortion both from the TV speaker and microphone,
    which can't reproduce the tape signals very well.
  </p>
</topic>
